[Music]
Friends, in the Bijli video, we will discuss life
insurance, then life
insurance,
what is time insurance, who should take it,
which is the best life insurance company,
but today we will learn in this video
[Music] [
Music] The
hospital bill is not yours to pay,
that bill is borne by the insurance agency, along with this you
get the benefit of pre- and post-hospitalization, that is, the cost of
diagnosis, routine
checkup by the doctor, all these expenses are
borne by the insurance agency, along with this the
cost of ICU, surgery, room rent,
ambulance etc., all these expenses are
borne by the insurance agency, friends, this is the
benefit of taking health insurance,
after this let us now know
how many types of head
insurance are available in India, there are about six
types of insurance in India, first is individual
health insurance, it is clear from the name itself,
an individual is included in this health
insurance, but if the person
wishes, he can also include his parents, wife and children in the policy,
then along with that  The insurance policy is
flooded with insurance coverage. Let's understand this with an example. Suppose
your
insurance amount is ₹10,000 and you
include three more family members in the policy, then the health
insurance will
increase from ₹1 lakh to ₹40 lakh. This ₹
40 lakh sum assured can be used by family members
separately. The second is
family health insurance. In this health
insurance policy, the entire family gets a
single health insurance.
One disadvantage of this policy is that
if the sum assured in the policy is completely spent on one family member, then the
other family members do
not get a chance to use this policy.
Therefore, if you have elderly people in your house,
then it would be better to take a separate health insurance for them. The
third is
senior citizen health insurance. It is for those people
whose age is above 60 years. Due to old
age, they often remain homeless,
hence this policy
also provides the benefit of comprehensive coverage. The fourth is group
health insurance. This insurance policy is taken by a
company or any such organization to retain its employees.  The employee
gets the benefit of this policy as long as
he works in this company. If
that employee leaves the company, then the
employee insurance gets red and the
fifth is Battery Insurance Plus Health
Insurance policy only
for pregnant ladies. The policy is from 10 years of pregnancy
till 3 months after the birth of the child.
Whatever medical bill is incurred during the policy period, the
insurance company bears the entire insurance but there is
a problem in this policy that there is a
waiting period of two years and on the sixth there
is top up health insurance. Top up plan is
taken along with the basic plan for extra benefit. Top up means
extension. Let us understand this with an example. There is a
person taking a loan. He has
taken an assignment of Rs.
5 lakh and along with it a top plan of Rs. 5 lakh and due to some reason
his medical bill is ₹6 lakh. So
in such a situation, ₹5 lakh will be borne by him from his basic plan
and the remaining ₹1 lakh will be borne by him.
This is the benefit of top up plan.
Now let us also know its disadvantages.  Let's
take this insurance. Shabaash gets insured again
and his medical bill is ₹1 lakh.
In such a situation, he cannot pay with ₹1 lakh
because the basic plan of ₹10 lakh has already
ended. The last stop is yours. You will be able to
use the basic plan only when the
basic plan starts again.
[Music]
Many companies have started another plan
called Super Duper Plan. Let's understand this also. Let's take this
insurance again. His medical bill is
₹6 lakh instead of the top-up plan. In this case, ₹5 lakh will be
covered by the basic plan and the rest will be
covered by ₹1 lakh. This year, he gets insured again and his
medical bill is
₹2 lakh. But this time, even
though the person does not have the assigned suit amount of the basic plan, he can pay with ₹2 lakh for the top-up plan.
Super Topper Plan,
but there is an option that it is more expensive than the top-up plan.
Friends, this is
how many types of health insurance are there?
Let's now find out
what we need to check before buying health insurance
and also select the best health
insurance. To select, we will
first look at the net worth of the
hospital, that is, how many hospitals he has with the insurance company. The
more types of hospitals he has with the insurance company, the
better it is for us, the better the chance of
getting a cashless claim. Its
advantage is that it will not take much time to pay the hospital bill. The
lower the tax or the less the network hospital, the better it is
for us because when we have to
pay the hospital bill, then we will have to show the hospital bill to the
insurance company, only then
we will get the claim. Therefore, the
more network hospitals there are, the
better it is. Let's take a look at the chart. This
chart has the names of some of the well-known
insurance companies of India. All the charts shown in the video are
from the government website of all of them. The final sale is of Rs. 22.
Now, from this chart, we have to find the
company with the maximum network hospital.
Then, the first one that comes in front of us
is Star Health Midi Classic Gold,
which has a network hospital of
more than 13,000. The second one is HDFC Cargo Suraksha
Platina, which has a network hospital of more than 12,000.  The
third highest is SBI General Arogya
whose premium is more than ₹10,000 and ₹900. The
fourth is 50 Line Supreme whose premium is more than ₹8,000. The third highest is
Tata Egg Medicare
whose premium is more than ₹7,200. The smallest is
United India Platinum Plan whose premium is
more than ₹3,000 and Sardhav
whose premium is more than ₹2,900.
Here Star Health, HDFC Air Co and
SBI General, these three private companies have the
highest network hospitals and on the other
hand, United India and Oriental India, these
two government companies have the lowest network hospitals.
Now the second parameter we have to look at
is No Claim Bonus. No Claim Bonus means that
you paid the premium to the insurance company for the entire year
but you did
not make any insurance claim that year. In such a situation, the
insured gets some bonus offer from the insurance company and
bonus can be given in two ways, one by paying
some percentage on the premium you pay,
like you pay a
premium of ₹10,000 and you get ₹
500 or ₹500 as bonus from the company.  You
can get a bonus of ₹1000 or it can be another one as
well. Your premium amount can be different
but you can get more health benefits on top of that.
As you can see in the chart,
except for government health insurance, all other
private health insurance companies have
given the second type of no claim bonus. Here,
HDFC has given the highest no claim bonus,
up to 200%. That is, if you
took a policy of ₹20 lakh and you did
not use that policy for 8 years, then
your policy will increase from ₹20 lakh to ₹400000.
After that, Tata Ag
and Star Health are at second place, up to 100%.
Bajaj Allianz and SBI General are at third place, up to 50%.
Now the third parameter we have to look at is the
room rent limit. Room rent limit or up to what amount of
room rent you can take is very
important. Let us
understand this with an example. Suppose you took a policy
whose room rent limit is ₹5000, but due to
some reason, you increased the room rent limit to ₹10000.  If you get admitted in a room of Rs. 10000
and your bill is ₹2 lakh, then how come
you will
get only half the money from the insurance company i.e. ₹1
lakh because you have increased your room rent
from ₹5000 to ₹10000, that is,
you have increased it by 50%, due to this your claim will decrease by 50%,
let us close this hand and
see the room rent limit, in Bajaj, HDFC, Tata and SBI
you can keep any amount of room rent as you want,
in Star Health you
can take only single private room, there is no limit on this also,
in United and Oriental you
can take room rent of only one percent of the amount of assignment seat, that is,
if you take a policy of ₹10 lakh,
then you will get tax on maximum room rate up to ₹10000,
now the fourth parameter that we have to see is
Vat Par Free Existing Disease, that is,
if the policy holder had any
disease before taking any health insurance policy, then in this case the insurance
holder will have to pay compensation for this disease.  The
claim will not be received, for that one may have to wait for two to three
years, the
lesser it is for getting the claim, the better. Here the
existing policy of Bajaj and Tata is the
least two years, HDFC's is three
years and the rest are Star Health, SBI, United
and Oriental's is one year.
Now the last parameter we have to look at is
maternity expense. Maternity cover means
whatever expenses are incurred during pregnancy
and OPD expense means
outpatient department extension means
expenses of illness during that time for which we do
not have to get admitted in the hospital, like it can be
practicals,
dental treatment etc. Let's
look at maternity cover and OPD expense.
Here in Bajaj the maternity cover is
75000 and OPD Express is ₹70000.
In Tata Insurance the maternity cover is ₹50000, which
means the insurance people will get one year
after that and OPD Express will be available at 5000
after that except SBI, in other companies the
internet cover and  You don't get the benefit of OPD Expand.
Friends, now let's talk about the conclusion.
According to me,
I liked Tata Egg and Bajaj Alliance among all the criteria.
People may need other criteria separately,
like someone
needs more network hospitals, someone may want more no
claim, someone may want a
tax on existing disease for even the shortest period,
someone may want a higher room
rent limit. In this way, you
can select a good insurance according to the criteria.
Friends, which health insurance did you select?
Do tell us in the comments.
Subscribe to the channel, like the video,
share the video with as many people as possible.
Thanks for watching the video till the end. See you in the next video, till then bye.